A Guide to the Carl George Kreiger Papers, 1930-1967
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Carl George Krieger Papers, 1930-1967
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1982-013
15.0 cu. ft. 19 boxes
The collection contains correspondence, speeches, notebooks, photographs, recordings, and clippings relating to the areas of agriculture, gas, oil, tractors, air and water pollution, waste treatment, and public relations.
Krieger, Carl George
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Carl George Krieger Papers were donated to the University Libraries in August 1982.
Biographical Note
Carl George Krieger (1905-1979) was a gas engine specialist and a pioneer in the development of the high-compression tractor. Krieger worked in the management structure of Ethyl Gasoline Corporation (1927-1969); was director of the Farm Equipment and Machinery Division of the War Production Board (WPB); was a special assistant to the WPB's chairman during World War II; and served as chairman of the Agricultural Development Committee of the American Petroleum Institute in the post-war years. A native of Portsmouth, Virginia, hew as the first agricultural engineering graduate at Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1926.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, speeches, notebooks, photographs, audio and video recordings, a scrapbook, and clippings and magazine articles on topics related to agriculture, gas, oil, tractors, air and water pollution, waste treatment, and public relations.
Arrangement
The Carl George Krieger Papers are in their original order. Boxes 1-2 contains biographical information and correspondence. Boxes 2-10 contain subject files. Boxes 11-13 include materials relating to Krieger's tenure at Ethyl Gasoline Corporation. Boxes 14-16 contain publications. Boxes 17-19 include training films and video recordings relating to farm topics.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Local Subjects:
Science and Technology; University Archives
Contents List
- Personal/Biographical Files and Correspondence.
  - Biographical and personal materials; scrapbook, 1933-1947; Correspondence, 1950-1954, 1954-1958. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1964, 1964-1967. (Box 2)
- Subject Files.
  - Tractors. (Box 2)
  - Tractors; Gasoline; Fuels and engines; Dauberman Day (31 July 1941, the 7th anniversary of the modern high-compression tractor); Farm market study; Liquid feeds; Pesticides; Farm advertising; Cotton; Farm program; Farm market data; American Agricultural Editor's Association. (Box 3)
  - American Petroleum Institute Committee on Agriculture; Milk Industry Foundation reports; Agricultural Relations Committee; "Brainpower Plus Horsepower;" Food for America (book published in 1960); Farm Book; "Food Business of the Future," 1958; "Food for Our Future" typescript; Letter re: Food for America book, 1960. (Box 4)
  - Letter re: Food for America book from the files of Charles H. Zeanah, Ethyl Corporation's Manager of Community Relations; Special edition of book; Agricultural publications. (Box 5)
  - U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Air and Water Pollution, 1960s; Proposed corn alcohol program; "Conservation of Air Resources"; American Petroleum Institute Committee on Air and Water Pollution; Air pollution legislation; APCA directory; "Freedom to Breathe"-NYC Mayor's Task Force; "Approach a Problem"; Pamphlets and kits. (Box 6)
  - Babylon, NY; Dr. George F. Kirkby's speech on air pollution control (1968) manuscript; 3 kits on the oil industry and air pollution; Four notebooks (Gasoline and engine emissions, c. 1940; training for air pollution control, c. 1943; position papers on lead, c.1950; API Comittee for Air and Water Conservation, c.1948); Testimony before governmental investigative bodies; Technical papers on motor vehicles: emissions, lung disease, public policy. (Box 7)
  - Publications on air pollution. (Box 8)
  - Publications on air pollution. (Box 9)
  - Water pollution; U.S. Public Health statement on water pollution; Waste treatment of lead. (Box 10)
  - Publications. (Box 14-16 (3 boxes))
- Ethyl Gasoline Corporation Materials. (Box 10-13 (4 boxes))
- Video Recordings.
  - Training film. (Box 17)
  - Twelve films and three tapes. (Box 18)
  - Recordings on a variety of farm topics; Film cans ("Masters of the Soil;" "This is Our Land;" Smog Control;" "A New World for Farming"). (Box 19)